<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The boke for to learne a man to be wyse in buyldyng of his howse for the helth of body [and] to holde quyetnes for the helth of his soule, and body The boke for a good husbande to lerne.</title>
            <title>Compendyous regyment or a dyetary of helth. Selections</title>
            <author>Boorde, Andrew, 1490?-1549.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16462</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3373</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844607</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844607</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9436</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16462)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9436)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 27:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The boke for to learne a man to be wyse in buyldyng of his howse for the helth of body [and] to holde quyetnes for the helth of his soule, and body The boke for a good husbande to lerne.</title>
                  <title>Compendyous regyment or a dyetary of helth. Selections</title>
                  <author>Boorde, Andrew, 1490?-1549.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Robert Wyer, dwellynge at the [sy]gne of S. Iohn̄ Euangelyst, by s. Martyns parysshe in the felde besyde the Duke of Suffolkes place, at Charynge Crosse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1550?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Consists of the first 8 chapters of: Boorde, Andrew. A compendyous regyment or a dyetary of helth.</note>
                  <note>Imprint fropm colophon; publication date conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (D4 is blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hygiene --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Claire Tolan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9436:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9436:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The boke for to Lerne a man to be wyſe in buyldyng of his howſe for the helth of body &amp; to hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de quyetnes for the helth of his ſoule, and body.</p>
            <p>¶ The boke for a good huſbande to lerne.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:9436:2"/>
            <head>¶ The table of this Boke.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THe fyrſte chapter doth ſhewe where a man ſhulde buylde or ſet his howſe, or place, for the helthe of his body.</item>
               <item>¶ The ſeconde chapter doth ſhewe a man, howe he ſhulde buylde his howſe, that the proſpect be good for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeruacion of helth.</item>
               <item>¶ The thyrde chapter doth ſhewe a man to buylde his howſe in a pure and freſh ayre for to length his lyfe.</item>
               <item>¶ The fourth chapt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan> doth ſhew vnder what maner a man ſhuld buylde his howſe in ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chewyng thynges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhuld ſhorten his lyfe.</item>
               <item>¶ The .v. chapter doth ſhewe howe a man ſhulde ordre his howſe, conſernynge the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementes, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort the ſpyrites of man.</item>
               <item>¶ The .vi, chapter doth ſhewe a man how he ſhulde ordre his howſe and how ſholde, to lyue in quyetnes.</item>
               <item>¶ The vii. chapter doth ſhewe how the hed of the howſe, or howſeholder ſhulde exercy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe hymſelf, for the helth of his ſoule &amp; body</item>
               <item>¶ The .viii. chapter doth ſhewe how a man ſhuld ordre hym ſelf in ſlepynge &amp; watche, and in his apparell werynge.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>¶ Explicit tabula.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:9436:2"/>
            <head>¶ The fyrſte chapter dothe ſhewe where a man ſhulde buylde or ſet his howſe or place for the helth of his body.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
               <hi>Man of honoure,</hi> or worſhyp, or other eſtate, the whiche dothe pretende, to buylde a howſe or any manſyon place, to inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hym ſelfe: Or els doth pretende to after his howſe, or to after olde buyldynge in to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyous and pleaſaunt buyldyng, not onely for his owne proper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyte. welth and helth, but alſo for other men, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wyll reſorte to hym, hauynge alſo a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his poſteryte. Fyrſte it is neceſſary and expedyent for hym to take hede what counſeyll god dyd gyue to Abraham, and after that to take hede what counſell God dyd gyue to Moyſes, and to his chyldren of Iſraell, as it apereth in the .xiii. chapter of Exodi And the .xx chapter of Numeri. And the .vi. chapter of Deuttonomu. And alſo in the boke of Leuites, ſayeng fyrſt to Abraham. Go thou forth of thy countre, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9436:3"/> from thy cognacion or kynred, and come thou in to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> countre. the which I wyl ſhewe to the a countre abundyng &amp; plentyful of mylke &amp; ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny. ¶ Here is to be noted that where there is plentye of mylke, there is plentye of paſture, and no ſkarſyte of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And where there is plentye of ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re is no ſkarſyte, but plentyfulnes of wod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. For there be moo bees in woddes, and ſo conſequently abundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny, than there be bees or ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny or waxe in the hyues in gardynes, or orchardes. Wherfore it ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that who ſoeuer that wyl buylde a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon place or howſe, he muſt cytuat and ſet it there where he muſt be ſure to haue both water and wod, except for pleaſure, he wyl buylde a howſe in or by ſome cytie or great towne, the whiche be not deſty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de of ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyties. But he the whiche wyll dwell at pleaſure, and for profyte and helthe of his body, he muſt dwell at elbowe rome ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge water and wod anexed to his place or howſe. For yf he be deſtytuted of any of the pryncipalles, that is to ſaye, fyrſte of water for to waſſhe and to wrynge, to bake
<pb facs="tcp:9436:3"/> and to brewe, and dyuers other cauſe ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally for peryll the which myght fall by fyre it were a great diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyous thynge. And better it were to lacke wodde, than to lac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke water, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> premyſſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderyd althoughe that wod is a neceſſary thynge not onely for fewell, but alſo for other vrgent cauſes ſpecyallye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſernynge buyldynge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peracyons.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The ſeconde chapter, doth ſhewe a man, howe he ſhulde buylde his howſe or Manſyon, that the proſpecte be fayre and good for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruacion of helthe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that a man ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue</hi> choſen a conuenyent ſoyle and place accordynge to his mynde and purpoſe to buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de his howſe or manſyon on. He muſt haue afore caſt in his mynde, that the proſpecte to and fro the place, be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt, fayre, and good to the iye, to behold the woddes, the waters, the feldes, the vales
<pb facs="tcp:9436:4"/> the hylles, &amp; the playne grounde. And that euery thynge be deſent and fayre to the iye not onely within the precynct of the place apoynted to buylde a manſyon or a howſe to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyties about it, but alſo it may be placable to the iyes of all men to ſe and to beholde whan they be a good dyſtaunce of from the place, that it doth ſtande co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyouſly. For the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyous buyldynge of a place doth not onely ſatyſfye the mynde of the inhabytour, but alſo it doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte and reioyſeth a mannes harte to ſe it, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally the pul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſe proſpecte. For my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte is ſuch that I had rather not to buyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de a manſyon or a howſe, than to buylde one without a good ꝓſpecte i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it to it, &amp; from it. For &amp; the iye be not ſatyſfyed, the myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de can not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentyd And the mynde can not be contentyd, the harte can not be plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, yf the herte and mynde be not pleaſed nature doth of horre. And yf nature do abhorre, mortyfycacion of the vytall and anymall and ſpy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rytuall powers do conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently folowe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:9436:4"/>
            <head>¶ The thyrde chapter doth ſhewe a man to buylde his howſe in a pure and a freſhe ayre, to length his lyfe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is noo thynge excepte poyſon that doth putryfye or doth corrupt the blode of man. And alſo doth morty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye the ſpyrytes of man, as dothe a corrupte and a contagyous ayer. For Galyen cerapentice no no ſayth, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we wyl or w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l not, we muſt graunt to euery man ayer, for without the ayer no man can lyue. The ayer can not be to clene and pure conſyderyng it doth cloſe &amp; doth compaſſe vs rounde aboute, and we do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue it in to vs, we can not be without it, for we lyue by it. as the fyſſhe lyueth by the water. Good ayer therfore is to be prayſed For yf the ayer be fryſke pure and clene a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boute the manſyon or howſe, it doth conſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue the lyfe of man, it doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte the bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne and the powers naturall, &amp; ingendryng and makynge good blode, in the whiche co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyſtyth the lyfe of man. And contraryly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll
<pb facs="tcp:9436:5"/> and corrupt ayers doth infecte the blo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, and dothe ingendre many corrupte hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and doth putryfye the brayne and doth corrupt the harte, &amp; therfore it doth bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de many deſeaſes, &amp; infyrmities thorough the whiche mannes lyfe is abreuyated and ſhortenyd. Many thynges doth infecte pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryfy and corruptyth the ayer, the fyrſte is the influence of ſondy ſterres, and ſtandyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge water ſtynkynge myſtes and caryn ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge longe aboute the grounde, moche peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple in a ſmallrome lyeng vnclenly and be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge fylthe and ſluttyſh. Wherfore he that dothe pretende to buylde his manſyon or howſe, he muſt prouyde that he do not cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuat his howſe nygh to any marſhe or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſſhe grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de. And that there be not nygh to the plate ſtynkynge and putr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fyed ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng water pooles, nor moryſh, but at leſt wyſe, that ſuche waters do ſtande vpon a ſtony or a grauellgrounde myxt with clay and that ſome freſhe ſpryng haue a recour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe to noryſhe and to refreſhe the ſayd ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge waters. Alſo there muſt be circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion had that there be not aboute the howſe
<pb facs="tcp:9436:5"/> or manſyon ſtynkyng dyches, gutters nor canelles nor corrupt dunghylles, nor ſync<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes excepte they be oft dyuers tymes mun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyfyed, and made clene: Swepyng of how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes and chambres ought not to be done, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longe as any honeſt man is within the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyncte of the howſe, for the douſte doth pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryfye, the ayer makynge it muſty &amp; dence. Alſo nyghe to the place, ſet nother hempe nor flexe be watered, and beware of the ſnoffe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>audelles, and of the ſauoure of apples, for theſe thynges be contagyous, and infectyue. Alſo myſtye &amp; clowdy day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es impetous and vehement wyndes, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belous and vaperous wether is not good to laboure in it to open the poores to let in infectious ayer. Furthermore beware of pyſſyng in drauftes, and permyt no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon pyſſynge place be aboute the howſe or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon, and let the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon howſe of element he ouer ſome water, or els clongatyd from the howſe. And beware of emptyeng of pyſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pottes and pyſſyng in chymnes, ſo that all euyll and contagyous ayers may be expel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyd, and clere ayer kept vnputryfyed. And
<pb facs="tcp:9436:6"/> of all thynges let the buttery, the celler, the kytchyn, the larderhowſe with al other how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes of offyces be kepte clene, that there be no fylth in them, but good and odyferous ſauours. And to expel and expulſe all cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rupt and contagyous ayer.</p>
            <p>¶ For whan the plaages of the Peſtylence or the ſwetynge ſyckenes is in a trowne or countre, at Mountpylour, and in all other hyghe regyons and countres, that I haue ben in, the people doth flye from the conta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyous and infectyous ayer, preſeruatyues with other councell of Phyſycke, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge. In lower and other baaſe coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tres, howſes the whiche be infectyd in tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne or cytie, be cloſed vp, both dores &amp; wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and the inhabytours ſhal not come abrode, not<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er to churche nor market, for in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fectynge other, with that ſyckenes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The fourth chapter, doth ſhewe vnder what maner and faſſhyon a man ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de buylde his howſe and manſyon in exchewynge thynges the whiche ſhulde ſhorten the lyfe of man.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:9436:6"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han a man dothe begyn to buylde his howſe or manſyon place, he muſte prouyde (ſayth Iheſus chriſte) before that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne to buylde, for all thynges neceſſarye, for the performacion of it, leſte that whan he hah made his foundacion, and can not fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſſhe his worke that he hath begon, euery man wyll deryde hym ſayenge. This man dyd begyn to bylde, but he can not fynyſſh or make an ende of his purpoſe, for a man muſt conſyder the expence before he do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn to buylde, for there goth to buyldynge many a nayle, many pynnes, many lathes and many tyles or ſklates, or ſtrawes, beſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de other greatter charges, as tymber, bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, lyme, ſande, ſtones or brycke, beſyde workemanſhyp, and the impleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. But a man the whiche haue prouyde, or hath in ſtore to accomplyſſe his purpoſe. And hath choſen a good ſoyle and place to cituat his howſe or manſyon, and that the proſpecte be good. And that the ayer be pure freſſhe
<pb facs="tcp:9436:7"/> and clene. Then he that wyll buylde, lette hym make his foundacion vpon a grauell grounde myxt with clay, or els let hym bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ylde vpon a rocke of ſtone, or els vpon an hyll or a hylles ſyde. And ordre and edyfy the howſe ſo that the pryncipall and chefe proſpectes may be Eaſte and Weſt ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Northeſt, Southeſt, and Southweſt, for the merydyall wynde of all wyndes is the moſt worſt, for the South wynde doth cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte. and doth make euyll vapours. The Eſt wynde is temperat fryſke and fragra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t The weſt wynde is mutable. The North wynde purgeth euyl vapours. wherfore bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter it is of the two worſt that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyndowes do open playne north, than playne ſouth, although that Ieremy ſayth from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> north dependyth all euyl And alſo it is wrytten in Cantica ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ticorum. Ryfe vp north wyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, and come thou ſouthwynde and perflat my gardyn, make the hall vnder ſuch a faſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyon, that the parfoure anexed to the hed of the hall. And the buttery and pantry be at the howſe ende of the hall, the ſeller vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the pantry, ſet ſomwhat abaſe, the kyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyn
<pb facs="tcp:9436:7"/> ſet abaſe from the buttry and pantry co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge with an entrye by the wall of the buttry, the paſtry howſe, &amp; the larder howſe anxed to the kytchyn, than deuyde the lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynges by the cyrcuyte of the quadryuyall courte, and let the gate howſe be oppoſyte or agaynſt the hall dore ſtandynge abaſe, &amp; the gate howſe in the mydle of the fronte entrynge into the place, let the pryue cham<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber be anexed to the great chamber of eſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te with other chambers neceſſarye for the byldynge, ſo that many of the chambers may haue a proſpecte in to the Chapell, yf there be anvtter courte made make it qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dryuyall with howſes of caſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, but one ſtable for horſes of pleaſure, &amp; ſe no fylthe nor dunge be within the courte, nor caſt at the backeſyde, but the dunge to be caryed far from the manſion. Alſo the ſtables and the ſlauter howſe a dyapery yf any be kept ſhulde be elongatyd the ſpace of a quarter of a myle from the place. And alſo the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke howſe &amp; brewe howſe ſhuld be a dyſtance from the place and from other byldynge. whan all the manſyon is edyfyed and bylt
<pb facs="tcp:9436:8"/> there be a moote made ahoute it, there ſhul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de ſome freſſhe ſprynge come to it, and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers tymes the moote ought to be ſhowryd and kept clene from mud and wedes. And in no wyſe let not the fylth of the kytchyn deſcende in to the mote. Furthermore it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyous and a pleaſaunt thyng to a manſyon to haue an orochorde of ſondrye fruytes, but it is more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modyous to haue a fayre gardyn repleatyd with herbes of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>romatyke and redole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſauoures, in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyn maye be a poole or two for fyſſhe, yf the pooles be clene kept. Alſo a parke reple<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyd with dere and conys, is a neceſſary and a pleaſaunt thynge to be anexed to a man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyon. A done howſe alſo is a neceſſary thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge aboute a manſyon place. And amonge other thynges a payer of buttes is a decent thynge aboute a manſyon, and other why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le for a great ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neceſſary it is to paſſe his tyme with bowles in an aly, whan all this is fynyſſhed, and the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyon replenyſſhed with impleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, there muſt be a fyre kept contynually for a ſpace to dry the contagy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous moyſtnes of the walles &amp; the ſauoure
<pb facs="tcp:9436:8"/> of the lyme &amp; ſande And after that a man may lye and dwell in the ſayde manſyon, without takynge any maner inconuenyen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce of ſyckenes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .v. chapter doth ſhewe howe a man ſhulde ordre his howſe conſernynge the implementes to comforte the ſpyrytes of man.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han a man hath bylt his ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyon, and hath his howſes neceſſarye aboute his place, yf he haue not howſhold ſtuffe, or impleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, the whiche be nedefull, but muſt borow of his neyghbours, he than is put to a ſhyfte, and to a great afterdele, for theſe men the whiche doo brewe in a botell and bake in a walet, it wyll be longe or he can ley Iacke and ſalet. Yet euery thynge muſt haue a be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynnyng, and euery man muſt do after his poſſeſſions or abylyte, this notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge better it is not to ſet vp a howſehol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de
<pb facs="tcp:9436:9"/> or hoſpytalyte, then to ſet vp howſholde lackynge the performacion of it, as nowe to ronne for maler, and by &amp; by, for ſalte, nowe to ſende for breade, and by and by to ſende for a ſhepes hed, &amp; nowe to ſende for this, and nowe to ſende for that, and by &amp; by he doth ſende, he can not tel for what / ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che thynges is noo prouyſion, but it is a great abuſyon. Thus a man ſhall loſe his thryfte. And be put to a ſhyft, his gooddes ſhall neuer increaſe, and he ſhall not be in reſt nor peace, but euer in carke &amp; care. For his purſe wyll euer be bare. Wherfore I do counceyll euery man, to prouyde for hym ſelfe, as ſoone as he can. For yf of imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes he be deſtytuted, men wyl call hym ſyght wytted. To ſet vp a howſe, &amp; is not able to kepe man nor mowſe. wherfore let euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loke or he lepe. For many cornes maketh a great hope.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .vi. chapter, doth ſhewe howe a man ſhulde order his howſe, and howſholde. And alſo therin to lyue quyetly.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:9436:9"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho ſo euer he be that wyl kepe an howſe, he muſte ordre the expenſes of his howſe accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rent of his landes. And yf he haue no landes, he muſt ordre his howſe after his lucre wynnynge, or gaynes. For he that wyll ſpende more i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his howſe, than the rent of his landes, or his gaynes doth attayne to, he ſhall fall in to pouerte, and neceſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te wyll vrge cauſe and compell hym, to ſell his lande or to waſte his ſtocke, as it is day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſene by experyence of many men, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they the which wyll exchewe ſuche pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dygalyte, and inconuenience, muſt deuyde his rentes porcyon and expences, wherby he dothe lyue in to thre equall porcions or partes. The fyrſte parte muſt ſerue to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyde for meate &amp; drinke, and al other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary thyngꝭ for the ſuſtentacion of the how<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeholde. The ſeconde porcion or parte muſt be reſeruyd for aparell not onely for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes owne ſelfe, but for all his howſholde, and for ſeruauntes wages deductyng ſome
<pb facs="tcp:9436:10"/> what of this porcion i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> almeſſe dede to pore neyghbours, and pore people fulfyllynge other of the .vii. workes of mercy. The thyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de porcion or parte muſt be reſeruyd for vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent cauſes in tyme of nede as in ſyckenes reparacion of howſes, with many other coti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyall expences beſyde rewardes &amp; the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of a mans laſte ende, yf a man do ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyde this ordre he may ſoone fall in dette, the whiche is a daungerous thynge many wayes beſyde the bryngyng a man to tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And he that is ones behynde &amp; in trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, he can not be in quyetnes of mynde, the whiche dothe perturbe the herte, and ſo conſequently doth ſhorten a mannes lyfe / Wherfore there is noo wyſe man, but wyll exchewe this inconuenyence. And wyll caſt before what ſhall folowe after. And in no wyſe to ſet vp a howſholde before he hathe made prouyſion to kepe a howſe. For yf a man ſhall bye euery thynge that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the kepynge of a howſe with his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, it wyll be longe or he be ryche, and lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge or he can kepe a good howſe. But he is wyſe in any conceyte y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll haue or he ſet
<pb facs="tcp:9436:10"/> vp his howſholde .ii. or .iii. yeres rent in his cofer. And yf he haue no landes, then he muſte prouyde for neceſſary thyngꝭ or that he begyn howſholde, left he repent hym ſelf after, throughe the whiche he do fall in to penſyfulnes, and after that in to ſyckenes and dyſeaſes, lyuynge not quyetly wherby he ſhall a breuyat his lyfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .vii. Chapter doth ſhewe howe the heed of a howſe, or a howſholder, ſhuld exercyſe hymſelfe, for the health of his ſoule and body.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that a man hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyded all thynges neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye for his howſe, and for his howſholde: expedient it is for hym to knowe howe he ſhuld exercyſe hymſelf both bodely and ghoſtly. For there is no catholike or chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man lyuyng, but he is bounde in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience to be more circumſpecter aboute the welth of his ſoule, than the health of his bodye. Our ſauyoure Ieſus Chriſte ſayth: What
<pb facs="tcp:9436:11"/> ſhall it profyte to man yf he get al the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de, and loſe hymſelfe, and bryng hymſelfe to a detryment. Wherfore it appeareth that a man ought to be circumſpect for the helth and welth of his ſoule, for he is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſo to lyue, that nyght &amp; daye, and at all houres he ſhuld be redy, than whan he is called for to departe out of this worlde he ſhulde not fere to dye, ſayenge theſe wordes with S. Ambroſe, I fere not to dye, for we haue a good God. Whan a man hath prepared for his ſoule and hath ſubdued ſenſualyte, and that he hath brought hymſelfe in a trade or an vſage of a ghoſtly or catholyke lyuyng in obſeruyng the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of god. Than he muſte ſtudye to rule and gouerne them the whiche be in his howſholde or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his cuſtody or dominion, to ſe that they be not ydle. For kyng Henry the .viii. ſayd whan he was yonge. Idlenes is cheife may<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtres of vyces all. And alſo the heed of an howſe muſt ouer ſe, that they the whiche be vnder his tuiſſion ſerue god the holy dayes as dylygentlye ſe, and more dylygentlyer, than to do theyr worke, the feryall dayes re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fraynyng
<pb facs="tcp:9436:11"/> them from vyce and ſynne, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellyng them to obſerue the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of God, ſpecyally to punyſhe ſwerers, for in al the world there is not ſuch odeable ſweryng as is vſed in Englande, ſpecially amonges youthe and chyldren, whiche is a deteſtable thynge to here, and no man doth go aboute to punyſhe it. Suche thynges re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formed, than maye an howſholder be glad, not ceaſyng to inſtruct them the whiche be ygnoraunt, but alſo he muſte contynue in ſhewynge good example of lyuynge, than may he reioyce in God &amp; be mery, the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che myrth and reioyſyng doth length a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes lyfe, and doth expell ſyckenes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ The .viii. Chapter doth ſhewe howe a man ſhuld ordre hymſelfe in ſle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynge, and watche, and in we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge of his apparayll.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han a man hath well exercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hymſelfe in the dayetyme as is reherſed, he maye ſlepe ſoundly &amp; ſurely in god, what
<pb facs="tcp:9436:12"/> chaunce ſoeuer fortune in the nyght. Mode<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate ſlepe in moſt prayſed, for it doth make perfyte dygeſtion. It doth noryſhe the blod and doth qualyfy the heate of the lyuer. It doth acuat, quycken, and refreſhe, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morye. It doth reſtore nature, &amp; doth quiet all the humours &amp; pulſes in man, and doth any mat and comforte all the naturall, ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall, and ſpyrytuall, powers of man. And ſuch moderat ſlepe is acceptable i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſyght of God, the premiſes in the aforeſayd chap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter obſerued and kept. And contraryly, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderat ſlepe and ſluggyſhnes doth humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and make lyght the brayne, it doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendre rewme and Impoſtumes, it is euyl for the palſy, whether it be vniuerſal or per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyculer, It is euyl for the fallyng ſycknes called Epilencia, Aualencia, and Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencia, Appopleſia, Soda. With all other infyrmytes in the heed, for it enduſeth obly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyouſnes, for it doth obfuſke and doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebulat the memorie and the quyckenes of wyt. And ſhortely to conclude it doth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbe the naturall, anymall and ſpyrytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, powers of man, and ſpecially it doth in
<pb facs="tcp:9436:12"/> ſtygat and lede a man to fylle, and doth in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>duce and infarre breuyte of lyfe &amp; deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly it dyſpleaſeth God. Our Lorde Ieſu Chriſte dyd not onely byd his dyſciples to watche, but dyd animat them and all other ſo to do, ſayenge. (I ſay not onely to you watche) but to all men I ſay watche. And to Peter he ſayd mighteſt not thou one hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re watche with me. Althoughe theſe holye ſcriptures with many other mo, the whiche I myght allyg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t for me, although they be not greatly refarred to this ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, yet it may ſtonde here with my purpoſe &amp; matter with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out reprehenſion. Theſe matters her: nede not greatly to be reherſed. Wherfore I do re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turne to my purpoſe, and ſay that the mode<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racion of ſlepe, ſhuld be meſured according to the naturall complexion of man, and in any wyſe to haue a reſpect to the ſtrength and debelytie to age &amp; youth, and to ſycke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; health of man. Fyrſt as conſernyng the naturall helth of man. Sanguyne and colorycke men .vii. houres of ſlepe is ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient for them. And nowe conſyderying the imbecilite and wekenes of nature a fluma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticke
<pb facs="tcp:9436:13"/> man may ſlepe .ix. houres or more: me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lancoly men may take theyr pleaſure, for they be the receptacle and the dredges of al the other humours. Secondly youth &amp; age wolde haue temperau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in ſlepyng. Thyrd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrength may ſuffre a bront i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> watche the which debelyte and wekenes may not. As I wyl ſhewe by a famylyer exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. There was two me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſat at the dyce togyther a day and a nyght, and more, the weke man ſayd to hym, I can playe no longer, the ſtronge man ſayd to him, fye on the bench whyſtler wylt thou ſtart away now, the weke man to ſatyſfy the ſtronge mans mynde, appetyte and deſyre playeth with his felow through the whiche he doth kyll hymſelf, the ſtrong man doth hymſelf lytel pleaſure, althyngꝭ conſydred the whiche I do paſſe ouer. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore I wyl returne to the ſycke man, which may ſlepe at all tymes, whan he may get it but yf he may ſlepe at any tyme, beſt it is for hym to refrayne from ſlepe in the day &amp; to take his natural reſt and ſlepe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night and to eſchew merydyall ſlepe, but yf nede ſhall compel a man to ſlepe after his meat,
<pb facs="tcp:9436:13"/> let hym make a pauſe, &amp; than let him ſtand and leaue agaynſt a cupborde and ſlepe, or els let hym ſyt vpright in a chayre &amp; ſlepe: ſlepynge after a full ſtomacke doth ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre dyuers infyrmyties. It doth hurte the ſplen, it relaxith the ſynewes, it doth ingen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre the dropſes and the gowte, &amp; doth make a man loke euyll colored. Bewale of vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious actes before the fyrſt ſlepe, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally beware of ſuche thynges after dyner, or after a full ſtomacke, for it doth ingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre the crampe and the gowte and other diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pleaſures. To bedward be you mery, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue mery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany about you, ſo that to bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward no anger nor heuines, ſorow nor pen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifulnes do troble or dyſquiet you. To bed<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ward and alſo in the mornyng vſe to haue a fyre in your chambre to waſte and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me the euyll vapoures within the chambre: for the breth of man may putryfy the ayre within the chambre: I do aduertiſe you not to ſtande nor to ſyt by the fyre, but ſtande or ſyt a good way of from the fyre, takyng the flamour of it, for fyre doth aryfye and drye vp a mans blod, and doth make ſterk
<pb facs="tcp:9436:14"/> the ſynewes and Ioyntes of man. In the nyght let the wyndowes of your howſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cially of your chambre be cloſed. Whan ye be in your bed, lye a lytell whyle on youre left ſyde, and ſlepe on your ryght ſyde, and whan you do wake of your fyrſt ſlepe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke water yf ye fele your bladder charged, &amp; than ſlepe on the left ſyde, and loke as ofte as you do wake, ſo oft turne your ſelf i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bed from one ſyde to another. To ſlepe gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uelyng vpon the ſtomacke and bely, is not good, vnles the ſtomacke be ſlowe &amp; tarde of digeſtion, but better it is to lay your han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de or your bedfelowes hande ouer your ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macke than to lye grouelyng. To ſlepe on the backe vpright is vtterly to be abhorred whan that you do ſlepe let not your necke, nother your ſhulders, nother your handes, nor fete, nor no other place of the body lye bare vndyſcouered. Slepe not with an emp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye ſtomacke, nor ſlepe not after that you haue eaten meate an houre or .ii. after. In your bed lye with your heed ſomwhat hygh leſt that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meate which is in your ſtomacke thorowe eructuacions or ſome other cauſe,
<pb facs="tcp:9436:14"/> aſcende to the orife of the ſtomack, let your nyght cap be of ſkarlet, and this I do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertyſe you, cauſe to be made a good thyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke quylte of Cotton or els of pure flockes, or of clene wolle, and let the coueryng of it be of whyte fuſtian, and lay it on the fether bed that you do lye on, and in your bed lye not to hote nor to colde but in temperau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. Olde auncient doctors of Phiſycke ſayth. viii. houres of ſlepe in ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer: and .ix. houres in wynter is ſuffycient for any man, but I do thynke that ſlepe oughte to be taken, as the complexion of man is. whan you aryſe in the mornyng, ryſe with myrth, and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre God. Let your hoſen be bruſſhed within and without: and flauer the inſyde of them againſt the fyre, vſe lynyn ſockes or lynyn hoſen nexte your legges. Whan you be out of your bed ſtretche forth your legges and armes and your bodye, coughe, &amp; ſpyt, and than go to your ſtole of egeſtyon, and exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate your ſelfe at all tymes that nature wold expell, for yf you do make any reſtric<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion in keping your egeſtion or your vryne or ventoſyte, it may put you to diſpleaſure
<pb facs="tcp:9436:15"/> in bredynge of dyuers infyrmyties. After you haue vacuated your body, and truſſed your poyntes, kayme your heed oft. and ſo do dyuers tymes in the daye. And waſſhe youre handes and wreſtes, youre face and eyes, and youre teth, with colde water, and after that you be apparaylled, walke in to your gardayne or in to your Parke a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande paace or two. And then great and noble men doth vſe to here the Communy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And other men that can not do ſo, but muſt apply there buſynes, doth ſerue God with ſome prayers, ſurrendrynge thankes vnto hym for his manifolde goodnes, with aſkynge hym mercy for theyr offences.</p>
            <p>And before you go to your refectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratly exerciſe your body with ſome labour or playenge at the Tenys, or caſtyng of a bowle, or paſyng weyghtes or plommettes of lead in your handes, or ſome other thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, to open the poores, and to augment na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall heate. At dyuer and ſupper vſe not to drynke of ſondry drynkes, and eate not of dyuers meates, but fede of two or thre dyſſhes at the moſte. After that you haue
<pb facs="tcp:9436:15"/> dyned and ſupte, labour not by and by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but make a pauſe ſyttynge or ſtandyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge vpryghte, the ſpace of an houre or more with ſome paſtyme, drinke not moche after dyner? at your ſupper vſe hyghe meates of dygeſtyon and refrayne from grooſe mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, go not to bed with a full nor an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye ſtomacke. And after your ſupper make a pauſe or you go to bed / and go to bed as I ſayde with myrth.</p>
            <p>FVrthermore as concernynge your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parayll. In wynter next your ſherte, vſe you to were a petycote of ſkarlet, your Doblet vſe at your pleaſure, but I do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertyſe you to lyne your Iaket vnder this faſſhyo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or maner, bye you fyne ſkynnes of whyte Lambe, &amp; blacke Lambe, and let your ſkynner cut both the ſortes of the ſkyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in ſmall peces tryangle wyſe, lyke hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe a qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ell of a glaſſe wyndowe, and than ſewe togyther a whyte pece and a blacke? lyke an whoole quarell of a glaſſe wyndo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we, and ſoo ſewe vp all togyther, quarell wyſe as moche as wyll lyue your Iaket. This Fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re for his holeſomnes is prayſed
<pb facs="tcp:9436:16"/> aboue Sables or any other kynde of furre. Your exteriall apparayll vſe accordyng to your honour. In ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer vſe to were a ſkar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>let Petycote made of ſtamell, or of fynſe wolfe, in wynter and fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer kepe not your heed to hote, nor bynde it to ſtrayght, kepe euer your necke warme. In Sommer kepe your necke and face from the ſonne, vſe to were gloues made of Goote ſkynnes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumed with Ambre degrece And beware in ſtandynge or ſyenge on the grounde in the reflection of the ſonne, but be mouable. If you ſhall common or talke with any man, ſtande not ſtyll in one place yf it be on the bare grounde, or graſſe, or ſtones, but be mouable in ſuche places, ſtande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſytte, vpon no ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de nor ſyt not longe bare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> vnder a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of ſtone. Alſo beware <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in no olde chambres w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſpecyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſuche chamb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and Rattes, and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o lye not in no ſuche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the whiche he depryued cleane from the Sonne, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ayre. Nor lye in no lowe chamber, excepte that
<pb facs="tcp:9436:16"/> it be bowrded. Beware that you take noo colde on your feete, and legges. And of all wether beware that you do not tyde nor go in great and impytous wyndes.</p>
            <trailer>¶ Explicit.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>¶ Of folyſhe Phyſycyons.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHo that vſeth the arte of medycyne</l>
               <l>Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ge his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the feelde</l>
               <l>He is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>So to take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſheelde</l>
               <l>We<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eelde</l>
               <l>Whiche to not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> knowe</l>
               <l>All theyr vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and lowe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>¶ Of dolorous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>partyng.</head>
               <l>¶ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> puyſſaunt</l>
               <l>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>age</l>
               <l>But th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> death dyd hym daunt</l>
               <l>By p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oceſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome ſtrayght paſſage</l>
               <l>Yea, were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of ſuche an age</l>
               <l>For he ſpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yther yonge nor olde</l>
               <l>Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fyerſe nor alſo bolde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>¶ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſcripcion.</head>
               <l>¶ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuche is prudent</l>
               <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> where euer he go</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:9436:17"/>
               <l>Gyuynge examples excellent</l>
               <l>Vnto them the whiche are in wo</l>
               <l>Teachynge them in all vertue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>That they may not in to ſynne all</l>
               <l>If that they hertely on God call.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>¶ Of Phyloſophye.</head>
               <l>¶ At this tyme doctryne is decayed</l>
               <l>And nought ſet by in no place</l>
               <l>For euery man is well appa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed</l>
               <l>To get good with great ſolace</l>
               <l>Not carynge howe nor in what place</l>
               <l>Puttynge the fayre and dygne ſophye</l>
               <l>Vnder feete with Phyloſophye.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>¶ Finis. ¶</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>(Imprynted by me Robert Wyer, dwellynge at the gne of S. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euangelyſt, in ſ. Martyns paryſſhe in the felde beſyde the Duke of Suffolkes pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce, at Charynge Croſſe.</p>
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> imprimendum ſolum.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9436:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
